Charles Menguy

Data science engineer with 6+ years of professional experience in the online advertising industry. Fluent in Java and Python, intermediate in C++ and Scala. Comfortable with Unix/shell scripting. Well-versed in big data technologies and applying data science techniques at large scale.

Work Experience

Since 2012

Senior Data Engineer for Adobe (New York City, United States).

- Complete backend development of a customer segmentation platform from scratch in *Java* using *Hadoop*, *HBase* and *Cassandra*, managing more than 10 Billion profiles. This was done by leveraging *Amazon Web Services* in multiple regions, in particular *EC2*, *EMR* and *SQS*.
- Development of a *Python*-based *data science platform* to provide analytics on multidimensional data coming from different data sources with *Hive* and *Redshift* processing dozens of Terabytes daily. 150+ Terabytes stored.
- Participation in the development of an algorithmic segmentation framework based on *Hive* using *TF-IDF*.
- High-frequency distributed multi-threaded cookie exchange service built in *Java* with a custom streaming protocol based on *SQS*, making tens of thousands HTTP requests per second to dozens of ad networks/DSPs/DMPs.
- Research and development of a cross-device stitching engine processing hundreds of Terabytes weekly via *EMR* and *Spark* using graph-based cluster algorithms, coordination via *AWS Data Pipeline*. Main development in *Scala*, analysis and evaluation via *IPython notebooks*.

2011-2012

Senior Software Engineer for Proclivity Media (New York City, United States).

- Development of a scoring engine using *Bayesian inference* to compute business value of website visitors.
- Using *Hadoop* and *Pig* to develop reporting infrastructure, and operational improvements.
- Implementation of a job controller to standardize the company's *Hadoop* pipeline and scheduling.
- High-frequency monitoring system to collect *Hadoop* metrics via *ZeroMQ* and analyzed via *Esper* to detect outliers and trends and visualized in *Graphite*.

2010-2011

Software Engineer for 24/7 Real Media (New York City, United States).

- Implementation of scaling improvements on a custom C++-based distributed system.
- Research and development of customer segmentation engine inC++.
- Modernization of backend using *MongoDB* after extensive benchmarking of several *NoSQL* solutions.

2009 (5 months)

Internship at GFI Informatique (Sophia-Antipolis, France).

Research on *image processing* techniques to recognize QR codes on mobile and implementation of a mobile virtual shop using *J2EE* technologies.

Open-Source Contributions

Python Author of ndopt, a library for optimizing n-dimensional spaces using particle swarms.

Author of griddle, a library for optimizing grid-like patterns using simulated annealing.

Java Author of the cloudwatch-metrics library to collect Hadoop metrics into Amazon

CloudWatch.

Misc My StackOverflow reputation is close to 20k, among the top 2% contributors, and top 5 in

the Hadoop community.

Open Data

I like taking open data apart to find something useful, andblog about it.

Author of crime-analytics, an analysis of real crime data from San Francisco and Seattle to

find temporal and geospatial patterns.

Education

2007-2010 MS in Computer Science in EPITA (Paris, France).

Top French school of Computer Science and Applied Mathematics with highly selective recruitment. Graduated with highest honors. Major in cognitive science and machine

learning.

2005-2007 Preparatory classes in Lycée Chateaubriand (Rennes, France).

Mathematics and Physics courses before a national competitive examination to Grandes

Écoles. Equivalent to a US Bachelor's degree.

2005 High school diploma (SAT equivalent) with highest honors.

Activities and Interests

Hobbies I like traveling around the world and discovering new cultures and ways of thinking.

I enjoy learning more about various topics, using platforms such as Coursera, Udacity or

edX.

Activities I have been teaching assistant at Coursera for several computer science and Al-related

courses.

Also a technical news editor at InfoQ focusing on the big data and data science topics.

Recommendations

Available upon request.

menguy.charles@gmail.com • +1 (917) 294-3487 • 28 years old • permanent resident 350 E 62nd Street, New York - NY 10065, United States